Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  - CNN News Broadcasts of Gulf War, Frontline: The Mind of Hussein, MacNeil-Lehrer News Hour Gulf War, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:00:00] (2 copies) (Box 353, Video-cassette ME116)
    00:58:00 Frontline documentary 1991 Feb. 26, The Mind of Hussein, going into the motivations and psychology of Saddam Hussein, includes interviews with Ba'ath party members, also includes a biography of his rise to power, archival footage, Iraqi opposition members, interviews with American journalists, academics, American officials, Frontline investigates the personal and political history of Iraq's Saddam Hussein. Through interviews with Hussein's former neighbors, members of his government, military leaders, journalists, and Middle East experts, correspondent Hodding Carter reveals the fears, the passions, and the intellect of the man behind the demonic image.
    01:58:00 CNN live coverage of the ground war in the Persian Gulf, military briefings, statements from Iraqi officials, coverage from the White House, Kuwait City.
    02:30:00 Macneil-Lehrer News Hour coverage of the Gulf War with news reports and military press briefings and interviews with analysts, coverage of end of the ground war, Bush policy.
    02:50:00 more CNN coverage of the end of the ground war, interviews with returning soldiers, liberation of Kuwait, Israeli fear of scud missiles, footage of troops pulling out of Iraq into Kuwait, situation in Baghdad.
    03:30:00 ABC news coverage of the war.
    03:54:00 Macneil-Lehrer News Hour coverage of the prospects for democracy in Kuwait, the situation with the palestinians and peace in the Middle East, interviews with analysts, Edward Said and others, Gary Sick, coverage of the troops in battle surrender of Iraqi soldiers, footage of soldiers in field, jubilation of liberated Kuwaitis.
    04:45:00 CNN coverage, analysis of events, footage of the liberation of Kuwait, soldiers in field.
    05:05:00 ABC Primetime coverage of post war in Kuwait, situation with Saddam Hussein.
    05:25:00 CNN coverage of post-war situation with American troops.
    05:30:00 MacNeil-Lehrer News Hour interviews with analysts concerning the Gulf War.
  - CNN, MacNeil-Lehrer NewsHour and other Networks NBC, ABC News, Nightline 1990 Aug. 14 - Crisis over Iraqi Invasion of Kuwait, NTSC VHS [TRT:6:03:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 353: 2 copies) (Box 314 and 353, Video-cassette ME117)
    Includes 2-180 minute working copies, 4-90 min. Betacam SP tapes (Betacam SP complete but working copy cuts off 3 minutes before end of second tape, see Betacam SP for complete).
    Reports from 1990 Aug. 14.
    CNN Coverage of Saddam's efforts to create a holy war against West, and against American troops in the region, Iraqi spokesman's statements.
    00:15:00 MacNeil-Lehrer coverage of events, Saddam's attempts at holy war, interviews with Arab journalists, coverage of Arab summit meeting against Saddam, Arab specialists interviewed Graehme Fuller, Fouad Ajami, Rabin, Bruce Van Voorst.
    CNN Reports on the build up in Iraq, and Americans stuck in Iraq after the invasion of Iraq, reports of situation in Arab countries, situation of Israel and their response to crisis, the Soviet response to crisis, the situation of Penelope Nabokov, situation of Palestinians and their support of Saddam, reports on Arab-Americans, all interspersed with shots of Kuwait, Saddam, Bush, Arab leaders, King Hussein, Mubarak, Asad, shots of invasion.
    NBC Meet the Press-Report on the military buildup in the Gulf and the story of the invasion of Iraq, with group of commentators, Prince Bandar Bin Sultan of Saudi Arabia.
    CNN Newsday Crisis in the Gulf, shots of Saddam's spokesman translating into English, reports from Cairo on the situation in the Gulf, Dean Fischer from Time Magazine.
    Interview with Turgat Ozal concerning Turkey's role and interest in the Gulf War, relationship of Turkey to embargo.
    ABC This Week - Interview with Iraqi UN Ambassador Al-Anbari with fierce questions from, then James Baker, Secretary of State.
    CNN Live reports from Cairo and from the Pentagon concerning troop movements to the Middle East and detained Americans and Iraqi demand for Israel demand to withdraw from the Occupied Territories in exchange from Israel, Palestinian support of Saddam, the Arab coalition, reports on strategic policy and support by Arabs of Saddam, "brilliant opportunity for the future."
    NBC Nightly News reports on Hussein proposals for ending the embargo and occupation of Kuwait, and measures in Iraq for marshal law, lifting of travel restrictions, report that Gulf War will hurt the US economy, Moscow reaction to crisis.
    CNN World Day dated Tuesday Aug. 14, on Persian Gulf crisis, attitude of American soldiers, impact on Jordan and politics, nations who have expressed reservations on embargo, and question whether Jordan will join embargo, reports on Iraqi atrocities in Kuwait, sexual attacks on airline stewardesses in Kuwait, stockmarket reaction to crisis in Gulf, Qadhafi reaction.
    CNN Evening News, calling up US reserves to go to the Gulf to protect Saudi Arabia, the use of gas masks in the Gulf, situation in Jordan, stranded Americans.
    Nightline 1990 Aug. 14 Ted Koppel the first Western reporter allowed into Iraq after the invasion of Iraq, the 3,000 Americans in Iraq and Kuwait will not be able to leave, reports on how Iraq is preparing for the invasion and to go to war.
    CNN World Day Proposal of King Hussein of Jordan, and the continued deployment to the Gulf, the issue of women in US military in Saudi Arabia.
    Nightline with Barbara Walters - reports on the detained Americans in Iraq, Barbara Walters, Mohamed al-Mashat UN Ambassador of Iraq.
  - Kurdish Tape #11, NTSC VHS [TRT:2:31:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 353: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 353, Video-cassette ME118)
    One Working copy with two Betacam SP copies.
    Interview with Kurdish victim of attacks by Iraqi troops, describing how they entered their houses, also description of prisoners held by Iraqis, jail in security prison in Suleimaniya, by various journalists in informal setting.
    00:17:30 Search in the countryside for graves, exposure of bones, digging up bones, SMB 3 dated 1991 Dec. 26 finding bodies, digging up they say Iranians from their identifications.
    00:29:17 More interview with Iraqi Kurdish military intelligence officers discussing his training and work with the security forces, he met Saddam Hussein personally, also about his work with the Anfal with the commander of the first army corps when Ali Hassan al-Majid gave orders for the Anfal, 1988 Feb., planning of a secret operation, aim to eliminate the Kurds, he was upset when he heard this, supervising various sections, says they discussed chemical attacks, prisoners, those suspected of being murdered, can be traced to the first army headquarters, said some were shot, heard sounds of being tortured in headquarters of first army.
    Second half of tape is investigation of mass graves, bones, etc.
  - Frontline: Spying on Saddam 1999 Apr. 26, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME119)
    In the wake of Desert Fox, the U.S. assault on Iraq last December, United Nations Special Commission (UNSCOM) - the special UN commission created to find and destroy Saddam Hussein's weapons of mass destruction - has disintegrated amid charges it was really a spy agency. Scott Ritter, former U.S. Marine and UNSCOM inspector, claims U.S. Intelligence destroyed UNSCOM's credibility when American spies penetrated and compromised the UN arms inspection teams. Frontline investigates Ritter's charges and asks, who really killed UNSCOM?
  - Frontline: The Mind of Hussein [1991 Feb. 26], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME120)
    Frontline investigates the personal and political history of Iraq's Saddam Hussein. Through interviews with Hussein's former neighbors, members of his government, military leaders, journalists, and Middle East experts, correspondent Hodding Carter reveals the fears, the passions, and the intellect of the man behind the demonic image, a picture of his mental state and stability. Includes footage of the famous Knight of the Long Knives speech in which he denounces Ba'ath party member immediately after his 1979 takeover of the presidency.
  - Frontline: The Arming of Iraq [1990 Sep. 11], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:50:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME121)
    Frontline examines how Saddam Hussein built Iraq's massive arsenal of tanks, planes, missiles, and chemical weapons during the 1980's. Correspondent Hodding Carter investigates the complicity of the US, European governments, and Western corporations in creating the Iraqi military machine the world is now trying to stop.
  - Frontline: The War We Left Behind [1991 Oct. 29], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME122)
    Frontline investigates the hidden strategies of the air war against Iraq and its devastating impact on Iraqi civilians. The program reveals how the war destroyed Iraq's power stations-leaving many Iraqis without electricity, sewage lines, or purified water, vulnerable to hunger and disease, and part of the 'slow motion disaster' in post-war Iraq.
  - Frontline: To the Brink of War [1991 Jan. 15], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME123)
    On 1991 Jan. 15, the United Nations resolution that allowed the use of force against Saddam Hussein took effect. Frontline correspondent Hodding Carter examined the critical decisions inside the White House, the State Department, and the Pentagon that had brought the nation to the brink of war. The inside story of how the Bush Administration decided to send troops to the Middle East just before the outbreak of the Gulf War, including day to day response of the US government. Interview with New York Times correspondent Thomas Friedman about the crisis in the Middle East and how America was in a reactive mode in terms of following what was happening in Europe. Discusses the events in Iraq and the American response or lack thereof to Saddam's criticisms of Kuwait. Friedman comments on the US stance of appeasement of Saddam. Robin Wright, Los Angeles Times correspondent, discusses the US miscalculation in terms of policy towards Iraq. Details the buildup of Iraqi troops on the borders and the infamous July meeting between Saddam and April Glaspie. Wright discusses the economic factors behind the invasion. Also shows Margaret Tutwiler saying in a news conference that the US did not have any security treaties with Kuwait. Wright says that no official stepped in to say that there would be any adverse consequences led directly to the invasion. Rick Atkinson, reporter for Washington Post, discusses the joint chiefs non-response. Ann McDaniel, Newsweek correspondent, discusses Bush's first responses on the day of the invasion and his meeting with Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher who encourages Bush to defend Saudi Arabia. Friedman talks about the importance of the Soviet Union's participation in the coalition and the joint statement issued by the two countries. Shows the footage of the Iraqi army in Kuwait during the first days of the invasion. Continues the day to day lead up to the defense of Kuwait.
  - The Testimony of Kuwait's Ruin, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:25:00] (3 copies) (Box 329 and 355, Video-cassette ME124)
    Film about destruction of Kuwait during the invasion and occupation by Iraq.
  - Oil Exclusive Report, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:25:00] (2 copies) (Box 329 and 355, Video-cassette ME125)
    Kuwait Television documentary on the oil fires after the Gulf War.
  - Peter Jennings Reporting: - Unfinished Business: The CIA and Saddam Hussein [1997 June 27], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (2 copies) (Box 329 and 360, Video-cassette ME126)
    Details of a covert operation to get rid of Saddam Hussein, with CIA Iraqi infiltrators, various interviews with Iraqi oppositionists, Ahmed Chalabi. Secret campaign by CIA a complete failure, government not willing to talk and the agency serves at the behest of the president. Birthday party of Saddam Hussein in April of this year, he wasn't there. Brent Scowcroft saying we wanted him targeted, approved by Saddam Hussein, shots of weapons attack on Saddam, Bush calling for killing of Saddam. Includes some footage of the end of the Gulf War, failure of Peter Galbraith to warn US of the rebellion, claims that US didn't know of plans for uprising. HIstory of the failure of rebellions. Ahmed Chalabi on expectations of rebels after uprising, shots of the destruction of Najaf after the war. Bush turns to CIA after the Gulf War, 1991 May, Frank Anderson, Near East Bureau Chief for CIA to implement plan for assassination, John Rendon, handled public relations for Kuwaiti regime, had relationship with CIA, using public funds, Hoshyar Zebari, failure to help the Kurds, US wanted no part of democracy in Kurdistan, origins of Iraqi National Congress, Scrowcroft says administration didn't think much of Iraqi National Congress (INC). The building of TV station in northern Iraq, Frank Anderson says the INC not a viable organization to get rid of Saddam, General Adnan Nouri, CIA asked him to work for them while working for INC. Clinton/Gore to seek to investigate war crimes of Iraqi regime, contradiction of coup and indictment of those encouraged to make a coup. Nabil Mussawi, INC. Frank Anderson sends in CIA people to northern Iraq to watch for trips to help to get rid of Saddam to approach the INC to help. Operative talks about desired access to defectors to debrief and learn about what goes on in Baghdad, plan to get units to defect. General Wafiq Sammarahi and the debriefing by CIA agent who they said was actually part of the INC trying to unify the opposition. Robert Pelletrau interviewed said he did not know about the operation in Northern Iraq, the London station of the CIA, CIA supported both sides. Pelletrau says CIA agent was a renegade who didn't have authority to make statements about support of Iraqi opposition. Hanging out to dry of the INC offensive, saying there would be no American support, the hypocritical stance of the Americans. CIA moved to support coup from Amman Jordan, Warren Mark, CIA agent in Iraq. Events leading up to 1996 Aug. 31 invasion of Kurdistan by Iraqi forces and civil strife between Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) and Patriotic Union of Kurdistan (PUK).
  - Good Kurds, Bad Kurds: No Friends But the Mountains, NTSC VHS [TRT:1:19:12] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 2 copies) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME127)
    Producer: Access Production
    Original Credits: Produced, directed, and written by: Kevin McKiernan. Camera: Haskell Wexler, McKiernan. Editor: Thomas G. Miller. Associate Producer: Catherine Boyer
    "McKiernan takes his roving camera to the front lines of the Kurdish rebellion against the Turkish government. At the same time, he tells the story of the Kurdish tragedy from the perspective of a Kurdish family in the United States, blending family chronicle with political documentary and lending the picture and unusually broad and dynamic range"-Variety review.
    Gives an overview of Kurdish problem in Turkey and deals with the story of the Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) and their battle against the Turkish government and it's campaign to brutally suppress Kurdish national aspirations.
  - Kuwait Tourist Enterprises Co.: After the Destruction, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:19:30] (2 copies) (Box 329 and 355, Video-cassette ME128)
    Producer: Kuwait Tourist Enterprises Co.
    Video montage showing the devastation of property in Kuwait after the Iraqi invasion and the destruction of the tourist industry. The video concentrates on the beaches and theme parks that were destroyed, devastating the tourist industry.
  - War Generation Beirut, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:50:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME129)
    Producer: An International Broadcasting Trust Production w/ MTC (Lebanon) for BBC
    Original Credits: Directed By: Jean Khalil Chamoun and Mai Masri
    This brave documentary shot on the streets of Beirut traces the life experiences of three generations of young people as they struggle to survive in the war-torn city. A truly rare insight into the thoughts, feelings, and aspirations of the "war generation."
    Winner of the Bronze Apple Award - 1990 National Film and Video Festival.
    A documentary focusing on the war in Beirut and the nature of the divided city and its consequences for the children of the city. Interviews with young children from East and West Beirut, including militia men and just other unemployed young men. Includes footage of the war, and shots of destroyed houses in Beirut. Also includes interviews with Palestinian youths who grew up in the refugee camps in Lebanon, including Shatila, site of the 1982 massacre of Palestinians by Christian phalangist militia supported by the Israeli troops occupying Beirut at the time. Also describes the prewar situation in Beirut and the great disparity of wealth separating poor Lebanese from wealthy and the civil war as an opportunity for revolutionary change. The roots of the conflict in the colonial time of the French who cause sectarian divisions that didn't exist before. Documents also the course of the war, the developing stalemates that led up to the 1982 invasion of Lebanon by Israel. Footage of the Palestinian fighters leaving Lebanon and testimony by Palestinians of the Israelis massacres in Sabra and Shatila on Friday, 1982 Sep. 18. Documents also the 1988 demonstrations against the war on both sides and against the leaders who have perpetuated the war.
  - Jerusalem: An Occupation Set in Stone, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (2 copies) (Box 329 and 355, Video-cassette ME130)
    Producer: Palestinian Housing Rights Movement
    Original Credits: Director: Marty Rosenbluth
    Produced by the Palestinian Housing Rights Movement, Jerusalem: An Occupation Set in Stone is a tribute to the thousands of Palestinians living in East Jerusalem without access to life's most basic amenities. Filmmaker, Marty Rosenbluth, details the devastating effects of Israel's urban planning policies that, according to many, aim to uproot the Palestinian presence in the Holy City. Due to it's fairness and clarity, Jerusalem: An Occupation Set in Stone? was awarded an Honorable Mention for the Lindheim Award in the Third Annual Jewish Video Competition - an award that honors programs that best explore the political and social relationships between Jews and other ethnic or religious groups.
  - Hostage of Time, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:50:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 355: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 355, Video-cassette ME131)
    Producer: A Future Television and MTC (Beirut) Production
    Original Credits: Written and directed by Jean Khalil Chamoun. Executive Producer: Mai Masri
    A young woman doctor returns to her village in Southern Lebanon. Through her relationship with her family and the women and children of the surrounding villages, we discover the hopes and dreams of the people of Southern Lebanon and their courageous efforts to rebuild their lives.
  - Children of Fire, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:50:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 353: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 353, Video-cassette ME132)
    Producer: An MTC Production for BBC Television
    Original Credits: Executive Producer: Jean Khalil Chamoun. Directed By Mai Masri
    When the filmmaker Mai Masri returned to her hometown of Nablus after a fourteen year absence, she discovered a new generation of Palestinian fighters: the children of the Intifada.
    Winner of the Award of Public at the Freminin Pluriel Festival, Children of Fire captures their courageous story on film and paints a daring portrait of the Palestinian uprising.
  - Women of South Lebanon, NTSC VHS [TRT:1:10:00] (Box 314: 1 original; Box 353: 1 copy) (Box 314 and 353, Video-cassette ME133)
    Producer: Message for Cinema and Television.
    Original Credits: Partially supported by the Council of the South. Directed by Jean Chamoun and Mai Masri.
    Women played a crucial role in fighting the Israeli invasion of Southern Lebanon. Wild Flowers, Women of South Lebanon preserves their stories on camera. The result is a poignant docu-drama about resistance and hope. This film has won several awards including the Film Critics award at the 1986 Carthage Film Festival.
  - Children of Shatila, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:50:00] (2 copies) (Box 334 and 353, Video-cassette ME134)
    Producer: A Nour Productions Film.
    Original Credits: Executive Producer Jean Khalil Chamoun. Director: Mai Masri
    Shatila camp first became known after the horrific 1982 Sabra-Shatila massacre, which shocked the world. Located in Beirut's "belt of misery" the camp is home to 15,000 Palestinians and Lebanese who share a common experience of displacement, unemployment and poverty.
    Fifty years after the exile of their grandparents from Palestine, the children of Shatila camp attempt to come to terms with the overwhelming realities of being refugees in a camp which has survived massacre, siege and starvation. Documentary filmmaker, Mai Masri focuses on the lives of two Palestinian children: Farah, age 11 and Issa, age 12. Given video cameras, the two express the realities of their daily lives and their history. Their ideas and creativity guide the film at every stage. Out of their personal narratives evolves the story of the camp as a whole and through their images and words, Farah and Issa articulate the feelings and hopes of the young generation.
  - Under the Rubble, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:40:00] (2 copies) (Box 334 and 355, Video-cassette ME135)
    Producer: Welfare Association (Switzerland). Media for Tele and Cinema (MTC). Mid East Council of Church (MECC). Rock Cinematographic Indus (RCI). World Stud Christia Fed (WSCF). Arab Development Institute (ADA). Oxfam.
    Original Credits: By Jean Chamoun and Mai Masri
    The 1982 Israeli invasion of Lebanon was a traumatizing experience for the city and its people. Under The Rubble is the filmmakers' harrowing attempt at telling the real story as it took place in Beirut. This deeply moving documentary has won the Special Jury Award at the Valencia Film Festival.
  - Iraq: The New Babylon, PAL VHS [TRT:0:04:30] (2 copies) (Box 332 and 353, Video-cassette ME136)
    Producer: Journeyman Productions
    The reconstruction and restoration by the Iraqi regime of monuments that tie Iraqi identity to the history of Babylon. Also makes the connection between Saddam Hussein and Nabuchadenezzar.
  - IMI Human Rights Alliance Press Conference Montage, NTSC Betacam SP [TRT:0:16:30] (4 copies) (Box 346, Video-cassette ME137)
    Original Credits: Editor: Dawn Griffiths.
    Montage of the IMI collection on Iraq made for the UN General Assembly press conference organized by the Human Rights Alliance, music by Peter Gabriel.
    Not to be given out or broadcast in any form.
    See also short version with title inserts at ME168.
  - Uncle Saddam, NTSC VHS [TRT:1:07:00] (2 copies) (Box 332, Video-cassette ME138)
    Original Credits: Director: Joel Soler